If I let you live,
Jika aku membiarkanmu hidup,
you would let civilization develop.
Anda akan membiarkan peradaban berkembang.
Will you promise that you won't do that?
Apakah Anda akan berjanji bahwa Anda tidak akan melakukan itu?
What the hell are you talking about?
Apa yang kau bicarakan?
Why would I ever keep a promise like—
Kenapa aku harus menepati janji seperti—
No, you would never lie.
Tidak, Anda tidak akan pernah berbohong.
Not to science.
Bukan ke sains.
Will you promise here and now, for all eternity, that you'll abandon science?
Maukah Anda berjanji di sini dan sekarang, untuk selama-lamanya, bahwa Anda akan meninggalkan sains?
If you do, I won't have to kill you, Senku.
Jika Anda melakukannya, saya tidak perlu membunuh Anda, Senku.
I can't do that.
Saya tidak bisa melakukan itu.
I thought that would be your answer.
Saya pikir itu akan menjadi jawaban Anda.
Do it in one blow.
Lakukan dalam satu pukulan.
Making me bleed out forever wouldn't be logical for either of us.
Membuatku kehabisan darah selamanya tidak logis bagi kami berdua.
Don't worry.
Jangan khawatir.
I'll bust your cervical nerve in a single blow.
Aku akan menghancurkan saraf lehermu dalam satu pukulan.
You'll be knocked unconscious instantly, and then you'll die.
Anda akan pingsan seketika, dan kemudian Anda akan mati.
I won't make you suffer.
Aku tidak akan membuatmu menderita.
I promise not to miss.
Saya berjanji untuk tidak ketinggalan.
Taiju-kun...
Taiju-kun...
Yuzuriha...
Yuzuriha...
Senku!
Bayangan!
Senku, if we'd met 3,700 years ago...
Senku, jika kita bertemu 3.700 tahun yang lalu...
If we'd met before this planet became a stone world...
Jika kita bertemu sebelum planet ini menjadi dunia batu...
You may have been my first friend.
You may have been my first friend.
Senku!
Senku!
Good morning, world
Good morning, world
Good Morning World!
Good Morning World!
How far have I walked?
How far have I walked?
Only the pain in my feet
Only the pain in my feet
Gives me a sense of the distance
Gives me a sense of the distance
The hope for a beautiful view at the end of a long night
The hope for a beautiful view at the end of a long night
Is what keeps me going today
Is what keeps me going today
The mountains of the gods, the palaces of green
The mountains of the gods, the palaces of green
The depths of the caves, the ends of the deep blue sky
The depths of the caves, the ends of the deep blue sky
I'll go the full distance, there are no limits
I'll go the full distance, there are no limits
To the ends of the world
To the ends of the world
Good morning, world
Good morning, world
Good Morning World!
Good Morning World!
Rid away the impossibility of the dark
Rid away the impossibility of the dark
An odyssey turning mythology into the everyday
An odyssey turning mythology into the everyday
In this painstaking journey, turning over every stone
In this painstaking journey, turning over every stone
We'll expand our world
We'll expand our world
Senku!
Senku!
Answer me!
Answer me!
Answer me, please!
Answer me, please!
No!
No!
This is wrong!
This is wrong!
It can't be!
It can't be!
You can't die here, Senku!
You can't die here, Senku!
There's no way!
There's no way!
He didn't suffer.
He didn't suffer.
I suggest that, as his friends, you give him a proper farewell.
I suggest that, as his friends, you give him a proper farewell.
So long as Yuzuriha could be used as a hostage, Taiju would never attack me.
So long as Yuzuriha could be used as a hostage, Taiju would never attack me.
That was the power dynamic.
That was the power dynamic.
But, Taiju, if Senku's death were to enrage you
But, Taiju, if Senku's death were to enrage you
and drive you to attack me mindlessly...
and drive you to attack me mindlessly...
I'd have to kill you, too.
I'd have to kill you, too.
Please don't lose your head.
Please don't lose your head.
Taiju-kun!
Taiju-kun!
Don't worry, Yuzuriha.
Don't worry, Yuzuriha.
I'm calm.
I'm calm.
It seems I have no choice but to fight him.
It seems I have no choice but to fight him.
Sorry, Yuzuriha. If it comes to it...
Sorry, Yuzuriha. If it comes to it...
It's okay, Taiju-kun.
It's okay, Taiju-kun.
The three of us made a promise.
The three of us made a promise.
I'm sure it'll work out.
I'm sure it'll work out.
It has to.
It has to.
Yeah.
Yeah.
Thanks, Yuzuriha!
Thanks, Yuzuriha!
Why did he throw it in the air?
Why did he throw it in the air?
The boulder is a decoy.
The boulder is a decoy.
Taiju, I can see you.
Taiju, I can see you.
No matter what you do, you've lost.
No matter what you do, you've lost.
Tsukasa is wary of me.
Tsukasa is wary of me.
He wouldn't dare take his eyes off me.
He wouldn't dare take his eyes off me.
But that's when I have my chance!
But that's when I have my chance!
Tsukasa-kun's instincts would tell him that Taiju-kun would protect me.
Tsukasa-kun's instincts would tell him that Taiju-kun would protect me.
I think he's right, in this stone world.
I think he's right, in this stone world.
But like Senku-kun said...
But like Senku-kun said...
Science levels the playing field for everyone!
Science levels the playing field for everyone!
It's black powder.
It's black powder.
Senku-kun left us...
Senku-kun meninggalkan kita...
...with science to remember him by.
...dengan ilmu untuk mengingatnya.
The three of us made a promise to fight together.
Kami bertiga berjanji untuk bertarung bersama.
Yuzuriha, Senku, and I...
Yuzuriha, Senku, dan aku...
fight alongside each other in this battle!
bertarung bersama satu sama lain dalam pertempuran ini!
Goodbye, Tsukasa!
Selamat tinggal, Tsukasa!
Taiju would never attack anyone.
Taiju tidak akan pernah menyerang siapa pun.
He wouldn't have expected me to take so much as a scrape from that.
Dia tidak akan mengharapkan saya untuk mengambil begitu banyak goresan dari itu.
Goodbye, Tsukasa!
Selamat tinggal, Tsukasa!
I see.
Saya melihat.
That's right, Senku. You said it yourself!
Itu benar, Senku. Anda sendiri yang mengatakannya!
If we need to run, we're running together!
Jika kita perlu lari, kita lari bersama!
I don't care what anyone says.
Saya tidak peduli apa yang orang katakan.
I know you aren't dead!
Aku tahu kamu belum mati!
You wouldn't die while you still have the goal of restarting civilization from scratch!
Anda tidak akan mati saat Anda masih memiliki tujuan untuk memulai kembali peradaban dari awal!
What's the point of fleeing?
Apa gunanya melarikan diri?
I shattered his cervical nerve for sure.
Aku pasti menghancurkan saraf serviksnya.
There's no way to revive him, especially in this stone world, with no medicine.
Tidak ada cara untuk menghidupkannya kembali, terutama di dunia batu ini, tanpa obat.
Heart massage...
Pijat jantung...
I don't even know if I'm doing it right.
Aku bahkan tidak tahu apakah aku melakukannya dengan benar.
But I have to do it.
Tapi aku harus melakukannya.
Wait, artificial respiration?
Tunggu, pernapasan buatan?
I think you should keep his neck still!
Saya pikir Anda harus menjaga lehernya tetap diam!
Tsukasa-kun hit him in the neck.
Tsukasa-kun memukul lehernya.
Senku-kun sacrificed himself for me.
Senku-kun mengorbankan dirinya untukku.
Senku sacrificed himself for you?
Senku mengorbankan dirinya untukmu?
Magic Psychology Asagiri Gen
Psikologi Sihir Asagiri Gen
Here's a psychology quiz.
Berikut kuis psikologi.
Suppose there's an accident,
Misalkan ada kecelakaan,
and only you, your friend, or your lover can be saved.
dan hanya Anda, teman Anda, atau kekasih Anda yang bisa diselamatkan.
What would you do?
Apa yang akan kamu lakukan?
I think I'd get stuck trying to decide between my friend and my lover.
Saya pikir saya akan terjebak mencoba untuk memutuskan antara teman saya dan kekasih saya.
Wouldn't you obviously choose yourself?
Bukankah Anda jelas memilih diri sendiri?
How could you ever choose?
Bagaimana Anda bisa memilih?
What kind of nasty quiz is that?
Kuis jahat macam apa itu?
I'd say everyone.
Saya akan mengatakan semua orang.
I'd look for a fundamental rule that lets us all be saved.
Saya akan mencari aturan dasar yang memungkinkan kita semua diselamatkan.
Wow! Just the kind of thing a science club president would say.
Wow! Persis seperti yang akan dikatakan presiden klub sains.
Wait, that's allowed?
Tunggu, itu diperbolehkan?
That's my choice, too, then!
Itu juga pilihanku, kalau begitu!
This psych quiz tells you who is the most important to you.
Kuis psikologi ini memberi tahu Anda siapa yang paling penting bagi Anda.
That's ten billion percent obvious.
Itu sepuluh miliar persen jelas.
That book's absolute trash.
Buku itu benar-benar sampah.
Senku would never kill himself.
Senku tidak akan pernah bunuh diri.
He'd never sacrifice himself, either.
Dia juga tidak akan pernah mengorbankan dirinya.
He would have bet on some way we'd all be saved.
Dia akan bertaruh pada beberapa cara kita semua akan diselamatkan.
Try to remember about Senku.
Coba ingat-ingat tentang Senku.
We're his friends. We'd know.
Kami temannya. Kami akan tahu.
There must be a hint!
Pasti ada petunjuk!
His neck...
Lehernya...
I think Senku-kun was deliberately inviting Tsukasa-kun to attack his neck.
Saya pikir Senku-kun sengaja mengundang Tsukasa-kun untuk menyerang lehernya.
That thing he was doing...
Hal itu dia lakukan...
That's not a habit he's always had.
Itu bukan kebiasaan yang selalu dia miliki.
Why did he keep touching his neck and cracking it like that?
Mengapa dia terus menyentuh lehernya dan memecahkannya seperti itu?
There's a little bit of petrification left on his neck!
Ada sedikit membatu yang tersisa di lehernya!
When we were removing the petrification on your foot, didn't Senku say...
Saat kami menghilangkan membatu di kakimu, bukankah Senku bilang...
that small breaks are repaired when the petrification is undone?
bahwa kerusakan kecil diperbaiki saat membatu dihilangkan?
Taiju-kun, the revival fluid!
Taiju-kun, cairan kebangkitan!
Yeah!
Ya!
It might work on Senku-kun's neck, too.
Mungkin bekerja di leher Senku-kun juga.
It might fix his neck when the petrification is undone.
Ini mungkin memperbaiki lehernya ketika membatu dibatalkan.
The petrification's gone!
Pembatuan itu hilang!
Wake up!
Bangun!
I know you wouldn't die in a place like this!
Aku tahu kau tidak akan mati di tempat seperti ini!
Senku, you're...
Senku, kamu...
the star of hope for humanity, for civilization!
bintang harapan bagi kemanusiaan, untuk peradaban!
Please!
Silahkan!
Come back!
Kembali!
Wake up, Senku!
Bangun, Senku!
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine...
Satu, dua, tiga, empat, lima, enam, tujuh, delapan, sembilan...
All right.
Baiklah.
I can make it past 800,000 seconds without nearly losing consciousness now.
Saya bisa melewati 800.000 detik tanpa hampir kehilangan kesadaran sekarang.
My brain's getting used to this.
Otakku mulai terbiasa dengan ini.
I've been frozen like this for 117,354,889,550 seconds now.
Saya telah dibekukan seperti ini selama 117.354.889.550 detik sekarang.
In other words, it's the 3,718th spring.
Dengan kata lain, ini adalah musim semi ke 3.718.
Starting in the spring is an absolute must if I'm going to be revived.
Mulai di musim semi adalah keharusan mutlak jika saya ingin dihidupkan kembali.
All right, if I'm going to get up, now's the time.
Baiklah, jika aku akan bangun, sekaranglah waktunya.
Get up already, me.
Bangunlah, aku.
Get up!
Bangun!
Get up, damn it!
Bangun, sialan!
I broke out!
saya pecah!
I'd love to be that boisterous, but...
Aku ingin menjadi yang riuh, tapi...
I'm ten billion percent sure I would've done that if I were a simpleton like Taiju.
Saya sepuluh miliar persen yakin saya akan melakukannya jika saya adalah orang bodoh seperti Taiju.
My first priority is to secure my surroundings.
Prioritas pertama saya adalah mengamankan lingkungan saya.
My own body is a hint that's worth its weight in gold.
Tubuhku sendiri adalah petunjuk yang sepadan dengan bobotnya dalam emas.
The location where I was lying down, my position...
Lokasi di mana saya berbaring, posisi saya ...
The order in which the mystery stone fragments fell off of me...
Urutan pecahan batu misteri jatuh dariku...
I'm going to keep every last piece for when I'm ready to investigate.
Saya akan menyimpan setiap bagian terakhir ketika saya siap untuk menyelidiki.
Yo, where you from?
Yo, kamu dari mana?
Where are you from, monkey?
Dari mana asalmu, monyet?
Dude, he's all shiny!
Bung, dia semua berkilau!
Gross!
Kotor!
That monkey's got shiny skin!
Monyet itu punya kulit mengkilap!
He's got his nasty peepee out, too!
Dia juga mengeluarkan intip jahatnya!
So do I, actually.
Aku juga sebenarnya.
Gross!
Kotor!
Am I the first one they've seen?
Apakah saya orang pertama yang mereka lihat?
It doesn't look like civilization survived.
Sepertinya peradaban tidak bertahan.
Which means I'm the first shiny monkey to be born on this planet.
Yang berarti aku monyet mengkilap pertama yang lahir di planet ini.
This is exhilarating.
Ini menggembirakan.
It's been 117,354,893,870 seconds since I was petrified.
Sudah 117.354.893.870 detik sejak aku ketakutan.
The mental arithmetic is getting hard.
Aritmatika mental semakin sulit.
The leap seconds are a pain in the ass.
Detik kabisat sangat menyebalkan.
Not to mention, Earth is rotating
Belum lagi, Bumi berputar
seventeen millionths of a second slower every year.
tujuh belas juta detik lebih lambat setiap tahun.
Little numbers don't mean anything.
Angka kecil tidak berarti apa-apa.
AD 5738 April 1
Tahun 5738 M 1 April
AD 5738, April 1st.
5738 M, 1 April.
Today is Year Zero.
Hari ini adalah Tahun Nol.
It all starts here.
Semuanya dimulai di sini.
Take a look at the power of the shiny monkey.
Lihatlah kekuatan monyet mengkilap.
I'm going to build a civilization with enough technology to take us to space.
Saya akan membangun peradaban dengan teknologi yang cukup untuk membawa kita ke luar angkasa.
He's been rubbing that stick this whole time.
Dia telah menggosok tongkat itu selama ini.
That shiny monkey's a dumb-dumb.
Monyet mengkilap itu bodoh-bodoh.
Let's go home.
Mari kita pulang.
What a moron.
Betapa bodohnya.
I'm neither a meathead like Taiju
Aku bukan orang bodoh seperti Taiju
nor an ultra-dexterous craft club kid like Yuzuriha.
atau anak klub kerajinan yang sangat cekatan seperti Yuzuriha.
There's no way I'm going to start a fire
Tidak mungkin aku akan menyalakan api
using a primitive hand drill in Japan's humidity.
menggunakan bor tangan primitif dalam kelembaban Jepang.
That's right.
Betul sekali.
This shiny monkey has neither fangs nor claws.
Monyet mengkilap ini tidak memiliki taring atau cakar.
All I can do is improvise, one step at a time.
Yang bisa saya lakukan hanyalah berimprovisasi, selangkah demi selangkah.
That's exactly what civilization is.
Persis seperti itulah peradaban.
Why does he keep banging the rock like that?
Kenapa dia terus memukul-mukul batu seperti itu?
That shiny monkey's definitely a dumb-dumb.
Monyet mengkilap itu benar-benar bodoh.
There's some trick to it that I'll only learn through trial and error.
Ada beberapa trik yang hanya akan saya pelajari melalui trial and error.
Bash the edges off mid-air.
Hancurkan ujung-ujungnya di udara.
Sharpen both sides of the edge by striking it on top of a surface.
Pertajam kedua sisi tepi dengan memukulnya di atas permukaan.
I have to use the right kind of rock for the job, too.
Saya juga harus menggunakan jenis batu yang tepat untuk pekerjaan itu.
This colorful rock, chert, is tough as hell.
Batu berwarna-warni ini, rijang, sangat keras.
Nothing will work better for making a small knife.
Tidak ada yang akan bekerja lebih baik untuk membuat pisau kecil.
Learn everything.
Pelajari semuanya.
Try everything.
Cobalah semuanya.
\h\h\hShiny Monkey \h\h\hacquired \h\h\hStone Tools!!
\h\h\hMonyet Mengkilap \h\h\hacquired \h\h\hAlat Batu!!
I can unravel this like string cheese.
Saya bisa mengungkap ini seperti keju string.
Now he's twisting it.
Sekarang dia memutarnya.
I bet his brain is shiny, too.
Aku yakin otaknya juga mengkilap.
\h\h\hShiny Monkey \h\h\hacquired \h\h\hRope!!
\h\h\hMonyet Mengkilap \h\h\hacquired \h\h\hTali!!
There are actually quite a few animals that use tools.
Sebenarnya ada beberapa hewan yang menggunakan alat.
Crows, otters, and orangutans, for example.
Gagak, berang-berang, dan orangutan, misalnya.
But there's only one species that uses science.
Tapi hanya ada satu spesies yang menggunakan ilmu pengetahuan.
Generating heat by using the oxidation of the gases given off by cellulose...
Menghasilkan panas dengan menggunakan oksidasi gas yang dilepaskan oleh selulosa...
In other words...
Dengan kata lain...
combustion!
pembakaran!
\h\h\hShiny Monkey \h\h\hacquired \h\h\hFire!!
\h\h\hMonyet Mengkilap \h\h\hacquired \h\h\hApi!!
I use ingenuity to take in everything the universe has to offer.
Saya menggunakan kecerdikan untuk menerima semua yang ditawarkan alam semesta.
I'm the master of science!
Saya master sains!
I guess I haven't introduced myself yet.
Sepertinya aku belum memperkenalkan diri.
Nice to meet you.
Senang bertemu denganmu.
What the hell is that?!
Apa-apaan itu?!
The shiny monkey isn't shiny anymore!
Monyet mengkilap tidak mengkilap lagi!
I'm the only one of my kind on this planet...
Aku satu-satunya dari jenisku di planet ini...
a human.
seorang manusia.
Acquired Food, Clothing and Shelter!!
Memperoleh Makanan, Pakaian dan Tempat Tinggal!!
I'm going to build a technological civilization from scratch,
Saya akan membangun peradaban teknologi dari awal,
and this is where it starts.
dan di sinilah dimulai.
Maybe I don't know what to do
Mungkin aku tidak tahu harus berbuat apa
Hurry up, my mind is on the moon
Cepatlah, pikiranku ada di bulan
Flying up to where the wind blew
Terbang ke tempat angin bertiup
In my hands awakens
Di tanganku terbangun
The passion overflowing
Semangat meluap
Just wandering through this world
Hanya berkeliaran di dunia ini
Your one shining pure
Anda yang bersinar murni
Could never be pierced with a rusty knife
Tidak akan pernah bisa ditusuk dengan pisau berkarat
I'm burning like a fire gone wild
Aku terbakar seperti api yang menjadi liar
The moment an arrow shot through my heart
Saat panah melesat menembus hatiku
The noise plaguing me was released
Kebisingan yang menggangguku dilepaskan
Everything was different from that moment on
Semuanya berbeda sejak saat itu
If I don't try, I'll never know
Jika saya tidak mencoba, saya tidak akan pernah tahu
Why do flowers bloom?
Mengapa bunga mekar?
Your voice echoes
Suaramu menggema
Tell me why?
Katakan padaku mengapa?
I just shouted to the sky
Aku hanya berteriak ke langit
But you are no no no longer here, that's right?
Tapi Anda tidak tidak lagi di sini, kan?
The life we confirmed that day
Kehidupan yang kami konfirmasi hari itu
You can call it a fleeting dream if you want
Anda dapat menyebutnya mimpi sekilas jika Anda mau
But I'll save you from a wounded today
Tapi aku akan menyelamatkanmu dari yang terluka hari ini
Two Nations of the Stone World
Dua Negara Dunia Batu Stone
Next Episode
Episode selanjutnya
This is a work of fiction, but the plants, animals, and production methods described are based on reality. Foraging and making things on your own accord is extremely dangerous and, in some cases, illegal. Please do not imitate without expertise.
Ini adalah karya fiksi, tetapi tanaman, hewan, dan metode produksi yang dijelaskan didasarkan pada kenyataan. Mencari makan dan membuat sesuatu atas kemauan sendiri sangatlah berbahaya dan, dalam beberapa kasus, ilegal. Tolong jangan meniru tanpa keahlian.